silly is the power of the people's vote
and I think the people should use it to
vote for hi there in this last none of
the above video I want to try to tie
together everything that I've said in
the previous videos and in doing so make
the case one final time for why I think
that voting none of the above in the
next election will be the best possible
use of your vote and so the basic
underlying premise is that we as a
culture as a civilization society
whatever are in deep trouble and that
wherever you look there are crises
already in full bloom or brewing away
and just to list a few I mean most
obviously front and center at the moment
is the environmental crisis which you
know there's an existential threat to us
all debasing the very substrate on which
we all depend and but there are plenty
of others that are the line up alongside
that this financial those financial
crises
there's the increase in extreme
political parties and polarization and
society at large
there's the continued rise in inequality
which then leads to things like
depression and suicide and drug
addiction and homelessness and
loneliness you know all of these things
are symptoms of a very deep blaze that
lies at the very heart of our culture
and so in response to that we need to
find completely different ways of doing
things
and there are plenty of people out there
coming up with innovative imaginative
creative solutions in light of new
understandings about things and so you
know solutions to problems like food and
energy production in sustainable ways
there are solutions out there already
and to regenerate the soil around the
globe there are solutions out there
already you know therefore many of the
problems biodegradable plastics and
there are plenty of solutions out there
which are ready for trial you know ready
to be experimented with Bart's everybody
finds themselves kind of stuck because
the way we do things at the moment is
through our centralized political
systems and so
to me that a very important first step
in getting unstuck is to disavow
ourselves of the notion that this is the
best way of doing things
reclaiming sovereignty in the notion of
individual and collective voluntary
responsibility that's really what none
of the above is about two main strands
that this number one recognizing the
fact that our current political and
choice-making systems are incapable
fundamentally incapable of sorting out
the mess that lies in front of us and
secondly that none of the above could be
a umbrella under which many many many
different people can stand and I mean
I've unpacked both of these things in
detail in preceding videos but I'm just
gonna briefly go over each of these two
things one more time in this one and so
first of all it's important to take
responsibility for understanding that
governmental systems are incapable of
sorting out this mess and this is
basically because of the idea of the
complex and the complicated that I went
into in video 3 I think it was in that
our systems of organization and
governments our governance are
complicated but the natural world with
which they deal with which they interact
are complex and these two things are
fundamentally incompatible and so you
know how complicated systems have buried
us under a pile of rules and regulations
and lead tables and spreadsheets and
laws and bla bla bla bla bla that nobody
can possibly hold in their head and
understand and the spirit of finding
ways in which we can peacefully and
sensibly collaborate with each other and
along on a large scale has been buried
under a massive pile of complicatedness
and the other problem is as well a
complicated is easily hacked and is
therefore susceptible to corruption
which is why we have a situation now
where our policies is entirely driven by
money candidates are selected by money
elections are decided by money
particularly in America but I mean it's
the same everywhere and this forces
politicians in
to a position where they are forced to
be duplicitous and lie I mean they lie
about their expenses they lie about
their affairs they lie about their
business interests they lie to cover up
their failures they lie to take us to
war you know they simply can't be
trusted and even good people who get
into the senior levels of politics are
so beholden to the various interests
that put them there that they can't be
themselves I made this point regarding
Teresa May and that you know the only
time she was actually a human being was
at the very beginning at the very end of
her Premiership all the time in between
she was complete automaton a complete
robot and it's also worth remembering
that even if their intentions were good
and honorable and they genuinely wish to
change things for the better you know
most of these people are simply not
qualified or experienced to be able to
do so as I pointed out in a previous
video when was the last time a farmer
was the head of the Agriculture
Department or a teacher the head of the
Education Department and so you know
these people are all lawyers and
economists and accountants and so on and
even if they wanted to they simply don't
have the know-how the vision the
experience the expertise to be able to
manage these things and the final point
I want to make on this in this section
is the adversarial modality of the
decision-making process and so under our
current political paradigm the party in
power or the group in power whatever it
might be
formulates a policy there may be some
argument and hashing out and refining of
that policy and then it gets voted on
right rather than you know so it's a
very very top-down driven and
decision-making process as opposed to
getting a group of people together
deciding on right what do we actually
want to achieve what does each group of
people what are their particular
interests in this what fundamental
principles and axioms can we all agree
on as a starting point and then build a
policy upwards from there this is a much
more sensible way of going about things
but the adversarial nature of the
political process makes such a
decision-making process
impossible for all of these reasons but
primarily the fundamental
incompatibility of the complicated
complex
means that this paradigm this whole idea
of how to do things simply cannot work
and so the first part of this is
understanding that the second part is
the idea of unifying large numbers of
people under a single umbrella and I
think none of the above has the has the
simplicity and the breadth to be able to
do that and again I'll just briefly list
some of the groups of people I'm talking
about so first of all the activists I
mean this is the community that I'm
personally coming from this is what my
perspective is all about I've been part
of the zeitgeist movement on a free
party The Venus Project and more
recently the game BC Gnaeus and all of
these or all of these projects have real
contributions to make to a positive
vision of the future but they you know
has slightly different takes on an
intent and you know they tend not to
collaborate but under the umbrella of
Nunnelly but they can all agree that
this doesn't work right and this needs
to be got out of the way so that a
serious discussion can be had about what
might work better and how to go about
experimenting with ideas and then
rolling them out when they're when
they're known to work another group are
all the non-voters i pointed out that in
the UK some 35 percent of people do not
vote at all now I think it's reasonable
to assume that they are simply not
motivated to do so and so that's 35
percent for none of the above right
there potentially if they could be
motivated to get out and actually do and
none of the above
lion and tick on their on their voting
card and another very large group of
people my mother is a perfect example of
this she votes every single election
because she believes it with her civic
duty to do so right but she doesn't like
but she doesn't like any of the
candidates she's not excited about any
of them and so there's a very lot
another there's another very large group
of voters here potentially who if they
felt that none of the above was a
meaningful cast of their vote could
easily be persuade to do so I think and
so you know I think there's potentially
70-odd maybe even 80% of the electorate
right there who could be relatively
easily persuaded get on board none of
the above
so final summing up if you believe that
it's just a question of waiting around
for the right if you get this power to
you know make things right then you go
ahead and continue voting if you believe
as I do that it's much much deeper than
that none of the above really is the
only way to go and remember this is not
just a protest vote I mean it is a
protest but it's much more than that
I mean not only does it take away the
mandate of the government it's also a
clear articulation of the fact that we
understand that this cannot work that it
is in the way that we need to do
something different we need to do things
differently maybe don't even have a
clear idea now but in order to figure
out how we need to get this out of the
way and have a proper conversation but
having of that conversation difficult
though it will be some might argue
impossible but nevertheless worth
attempting is also the beginning of the
path to healing as a society coming
together healing the rifts and the
divisions that have emerged largely as a
consequence of our adversarial political
process and so what is required I am NOT
this person unfortunately what is
required is for someone to see this
video think wow that's a really good
idea that that could really work and
start organizing something around it
like I said I am NOT that person I don't
have either the inclination the know-how
all the social media presence to be able
to do such a thing but that is my hope I
think this idea has got real legs and
real traction and for those of you that
have watched this series thank you very
much for doing so and as I say hopefully
one of you will be up and run with it
thanks
[Applause]